[Music]
thomas it's really
good to sit down and open into this
conversation with you
uh you've got the kind of
resume behind you that makes this
particularly interesting you know
speak about philanthropy philosophy
systems thinking
[Music]
and the particular interests you have in
seeking to sort of facilitate big change
but appropriate change in our time is uh
is really fascinating and so i'm very
much looking forward to
to this discussion with you i think some
key themes are to do with
emergence and perhaps perhaps in
particular as well this fascinating
concept that you speak about
collective imaginary and these things
i'd love to discuss with you
but
among these three books you've authored
the nordic secret the market myth
and most recently um the world we create
how do you kind of how would you congeal
that sort of
interest together in terms of
how you meet the world at the moment
sort of where are we and what's your
view
of it thank you to him
great to be on your podcast and thank
you for that very
deep question and not very easy question
not an easy one no no not an easy one
i should first um uh mention that
um the book the the nordic secret
that you you mentioned um uh
i co-authored that uh together with lena
anderson
and my danish friend and philosopher and
i really want to give her credit for for
the um deep work that she put into
making that book
possible so uh yeah thank you leona for
for that beautiful is there a
red thread um between these three books
yes
that there there certainly is and um
it is all about trying to
zoom out from our everyday perception
of the world to see
some deeper patterns in
in what is going on and
uh i know that you have had uh jordan
hall
on on your podcast and uh
jordan sometimes talks about different
levels of
this transition that um
some of us believe that that we are in
um and i think just during the last
couple of years
there has been uh a rising consciousness
about the fact that we are actually in
some sort of deep
transition uh brexit
uh trump and not the least the covid
situation
during the last uh half year has has
made
many of us realize that just going on
with incremental change within the
present system
might not be enough to well if i should
put it
drastically to to save our civilization
[Music]
so jordan is talking about different
levels and
i've written about five different levels
and perhaps i could touch
very briefly on the four
first levels there the the first one is
the sort of
societal change that is more or less
going on every day
it's like the societal change we've had
in values
during the last 50 years in the in the
west
that has been in many respects very
drastical and and substantial when it
comes to
the place of women in society how we
look at
minorities how both racial minorities
cultural minorities sexual minorities
and things like that so in in many of
those respects even if
very much of course still remains to be
done in those areas
we are actually living in a little bit
of a different world today than
than we did 30 40 or 50
50 years ago um but um
if we look at even a deeper layer we
could say that the level two shift
that would be what we uh went through
during the
industrial uh revolution when really all
um of society's production and the way
that we were functioning society
really shifted in in a fundamental way
and and some thinkers are talking about
the fact that we are in a
fourth industrial revolution revolution
so those thinkers would believe that we
are at least at the level two
shift today but then
if you look even deeper and i think that
the shift that we are
in right now is is even deeper than that
and could be a level three shift which
would be of the magnitude of
the enlightenment when we really shifted
our world view the fundamental way
of of looking and perceiving the world
and we went
from a dogmatic religious
worldview into a rationalistic
scientific worldview
and that worldview has of course been
very helpful to
humanity that is what has given us
everything from
modern medicine to
human rights and and democracy
but somehow i think that
that world view has served its purpose
but has more or less now reached its
limits
and that we need to not discard
science and and reason but look at ways
of complementing those
those very powerful ways of looking at
the world
with other ways of looking at the world
and we might come back to that
a little bit later and then something is
thinking
are talking about an even deeper shift
uh going back to
uh uh the shift that uh
happened during the axial age and that
uh
john verweger so well has described in
his
series the meaning crisis
and that was the shift in humanity
2500 years ago or something like that
where
in many places of the world more or less
simultaneously
we had a shift in culture and
understanding
developing a written language that
enabled us to develop
the major religions or philosophies or
the ideologies
that made it possible for humanity
really for the first time to
go from living in small societies by
or small tribes guided mostly by
instinct
to really put together a system
that would help us to see the world
differently but also
experience and feel the world
differently
to make it possible for us to live in
large societies in cities with many
thousands tens of thousands of
inhabitants
and even small civilized civilizations
so so that would be a four level shift
and these shifts
have all been in or the deeper shifts
have all been in this
what some thinkers call the collective
imaginary
and the great invention during the axial
age
was really to more systematically
form a collective imaginary that
intentionally
made it possible for us humans to live
in a completely different world
and of course during the enlightenment
also our collective imaginary
shifted and
this concept of the collective
imaginaries is a little bit
nebulous concept and
how could we best describe it and where
does it come from
well it comes from deep sociology
and i think that
the deeper the shift we believe
that we are in the deeper
we have to look as just mentioned
back in history to understand what is
going on
so we so we need to understand deep
history
but we also need to look deeper into
ourselves
and to understand deep psychology
which um is a little bit the different
psychological approach from the
everyday psychological theory or
kbt theory or things like that that
really goes down into both our deep
individual
unconscious but also into our collective
unconscious
and i know from listening to your
podcast that you are familiar with
union theory and jung is is
one of the psychologists that has really
uh
explored these deeper layers of
our our consciousness and are talking
about concepts like the shadow
and archetypes and things like that
so understanding what's going on we need
to look into the deep
levels of our own consciousness and deep
psychology
because these shifts do not only involve
society of course
it involves also shifting us as in
individuals
but deep psychology and deep history is
not enough
we need also to look at deep sociology
and
that has not been up for so much
discussions in in public media
not as much as deep history popularized
by
sapiens hieraris great works and
deep psychology jordan b peterson and
jung
deep sociology uh if i should name
mention
some names uh associated with that
starting perhaps with them with the most
contemporary
uh sociologist that is using the term
collective imaginaries
and that is the french canadian
philosopher
gerard bouchard who just a couple of
years
ago came out with the book that is
called
social myths and collective imaginaries
where he's really connecting this sort
of mythopoetical
level that jung jordan peterson and
others
are talking about with these deep
levels in society that he calls
collective imaginaries
the eminent sociologist charles taylor
who might be more famous than jared
bourjad
he came out with a book 2004 called
model so
modern social imaginaries so social
imaginaries
is his term for that but those that
really pioneered
these these ways of thinking that that
were
um two sociologists uh writing in the
60s
uh called berger and lukman
and they published a book in 67 i
believe it was
called the social construction of
reality where they'd really describe
this deep sociological process
where we as humans construct the
deeper unconscious levels of society
and this was now very abstract and
and also okay so can i can i give some
sort of
understandable example of what i mean
oh please i think we'll take the next
hour and a half to begin to put some um
some more flesh on it but i'm i'm with
you and i i think it's brilliant so
please
yeah so so the main thinking the deeper
the shift in society
the deeper we have to look back in
history to understand
the deeper we have to look into our own
psychology
to understand what's going on than the
shift needed in us and the deeper we
have to look into
the shift in in society and when we are
really deep on on the mythopoetic
level in society we are down to the
collective imaginaries
so an example um
we as humans in the modern world
we need both air to breathe
and money to be able to survive in
this world and for us as individuals
money and oxygen can almost seem equally
important and tangible and necessary
for us to to function in and survive
in the modern world but there is a
but there is a deep difference between
oxygen
and money and the difference is so deep
that you could talk about an
ontological difference that they are in
a philosophical sense
made up of completely different um
completely different kinds they are
properties of completely different kinds
and have to be understood in different
ways
so if we take oxygen even if
all of humanity came together and said
we don't want to be dependent on oxygen
any longer
we want humanity to be free of
dependence on oxygen
we couldn't do anything about that but
if we came together
all of humanity or even perhaps just in
a nation state
and said that we would like to change
the way
that we allocate goods in society we
don't want to use
money any longer we want to use
something else
then money would be gone tomorrow
so there is something very different
between these two
concepts and one way to say is that that
oxygen is a natural phenomenon our
understanding of oxygen might not be
natural but
oxygen itself is is natural
whereas money is a social construct
it's it's an imaginary it's something
that we humans have
thought up invented in our mind as an
imaginary
but it is not just in my individual
it is in our collective imaginary we all
believe
in money and the fact that we all
including society believe in money
makes it necessary for me as an
individual to actually
see money as something very tangible
when i'm checking out in my local
supermarket
i cannot just tell the cashier that
money is a
human invention and i don't believe in
money
no yeah money is sanctioned by society
and and
is therefore meeting me as an individual
as something
something very real and tangible and of
course
the little sad thing here is that we
sometimes
mix this all up so
if we look at oxygen and the natural
world
we sometimes believe that
the planetary boundaries
is something that is up for negotiation
whereas the market forces is something
we just as humanity have to obey
when it is of course the opposite
so coming to this realization that a lot
of things in our world
i would say the majority of things in
our human world
is actually just human inventions that
we can see from history
were invented sometimes consciously but
many times just by
pure accidents and and flukes of
of history and of course this is not
just money and the market is
nation states it's marriage it's
precedence it's or all of those things
that exists because we believe in them
collectively and should we stop
believing in those things collectively
then the nation states and
the presidents would be gone would be
gone
tomorrow and so with many of our social
institutions rituals
and um other things
and of course realizing this
then that is something that is very much
empowering us
perhaps not empowering us as individuals
but definitely empowering us as a
collective
and in these deep shifts in society
we have these deep shifts in the
collective imaginary
but in order for us to exercise this
collective freedom
that this insight gives us then we need
to be able to do collective sense making
in order to
to enable collective action and
collective agency
and as many have pointed out on your on
your um
podcast not the least john verweger we
are today
so bad at collective sense making and
the collective sense-making is
is breaking down so then
we all become sort of slaves under this
collective imaginary and because
we we are we can't make sense and we
can't talk about this and we can't act
on this
then we are losing a lot of human
freedom in that way our collective
freedom
to shape our collective imaginary
okay so that was uh that was a high
level uh
introduction i i hope we didn't lose all
all our listeners
there well well um you know i think it's
i think it's brilliant i'm very grateful
for such a
context in a framing you've laid down
for us
i mean there are so many ways i'm
feeling i'd love to
bite into this because
the the sense i get the the
um the agency that thinking in this way
can afford i think is a very um powerful
and beautiful thing
this this notion this this recognition
that we're so deeply involved in
creating our world is something that can
that can um that can work for us and the
world
if we can only so manage to
perceive i think um more clearly
to to perceive and interact with more
wisdom
and yet here's to add in something
not a spanner in the works exactly but
with
one way in which things get so
complicated is
when we begin to recognize that um okay
some of these aspects of the collective
imaginary take
money for example while there's a
lineage of our sort of
behavioral processes that have created
this phenomenon something like a habit
that we're all participating in
if we were in fact all to come together
it'd be very hard in fact to decide
not to use it anymore and what would
be underneath that and how could we
reorient
and there the collective imaginary of
course comes right back in because
we might seek to um seek to
uh shift something but actually the very
lenses which we then might um filter and
interpret the next choices we might
want to make are in fact as well
conditioned
as you've said there's it's the
collective imaginary something like
the um ocean is to the fish how can we
then
come into a right kind of relationship
with feeling the good flow
between you know humans machines and
nature without and and i think you make
a very important point that
that the the collective imaginary is to
us
like water is to the fish
we we do not have the
instincts or the genes to uh
automatically see
the collective imaginary i mean the
collect the collective imaginary is
completely
transparent to our our senses
so we so we need really to do that as an
intellectual
exercise but also in everyday world and
in everyday society
we are not trained to to see it because
for for us as individuals
it doesn't really have that much value
to to realize that that uh
money and marriage and
nation states and borders that they are
social constructs because as individuals
we just have to
uh yeah take this as a as a fact of
of life but it's really when we're
talking about political philosophy
and the collective decision processes
and i think that
it is on that level that more and more
people start to understand that
on the highest level of our political
processes
then things are breaking down and of
course the
environmental uh collapse is
is one of those um areas where people
are
waking up saying that okay so we all
want to do something and most of us
wanted to do something
why isn't anything happening anyhow so
how do we translate this
individual will of many people into some
sort of collective action and
and that we are as good as we have
trained ourselves to be
and realize during the last 100 years or
200 years since the enlightenment
our own individual freedom equally bad
are we today to exercise collective
freedom and and i would perhaps even
argue that we are
uh
less capable today to exercise
collective freedom
than than we were perhaps 50 or or even
years ago definitely 50 years
ago why is that the same
well i touch a bit upon that in in my
first book that you mentioned the market
myth
and and i think that is a a little bit
that
and i'm as you know i'm in former
investment uh
banker myself i i i built my
uh small fortune on um
building a banking business in
scandinavia and in
switzerland so i've been working inside
the market and been making money
successfully within the market
and and i should also say that it was
from
realizing that the market and being an
entrepreneur
in inside the market that it was
more useful for me to look at the market
as a sociological phenomenon
than to apply the standard economic
thinking the neoclassical economic
paradigm paradigm but this neoclassical
economic paradigm and also the
neoliberal paradigm
that is putting so much belief
in the market that the market has really
become a myth
it has been the the sort of the the
overarching
meta-narrative that keeps the world
together
today and in that way just like the
foundational myths of other societies
it's become a little bit of a sacred
sacred thing and of course the market is
super a super powerful tool
and can help us uh in in and has helped
humanity to reach this
level where where we are today and it's
super effective when it comes to
producing material things and
refrigerators and cars and and all of
those things
um but we have put during the last 50
years
especially the last 30 years a little
bit too
much belief in the ability for the
market to solve
all and every um human
uh problem and in that way we have
backed off from uh political and
collective
decision making in those areas where
the market cannot function and of course
any
economist or even any student of economy
at university
knows from the first course macro
economy 101
that there are categories of goods that
even in the neoclassical economic theory
the market cannot provide and
collective goods like military defense
for example that is a standard example
of a
collective good that the market can
cannot provide but has to be a political
decision because you cannot decide
to want to to buy military protection
for
two thousand dollars and and i would say
i want military protection for seven
thousand dollars no
if we have military protection everyone
is benefiting from it
so we all need to collectively chip into
to to finance it
so that's the standard example but you
could say other things like
for example uh even our societal
culture or our collective imaginary is
such a collective good that not even
neoclassical economic theory pretends
that the market could deliver on
another group of goods are the
uh what economies uh uh
called the merit goods which are goods
that you do not
that you have no chance to value or
appreciate the value of until
you have actually consumed it so there
also the market cannot
cannot function and and the typical or
example of that is personal development
so some somebody could could tell you
that yeah you should really spend the
time and the money necessary to
to take the next step in your personal
development and you might say
well what is this and that can possibly
not be worth this
time and money you are talking about so
um i don't want that
and and no advertisement campaign could
sort of convey
the the true benefits they could entice
you to do it
but they couldn't convey the true
benefits of it
until you've gone through it and then
you could say wow
i mean that this was worth it many times
over
yeah but you can't really explain it to
your friend yeah exactly no
exactly i mean so in those cases uh um
the market is not working so come back
to your question so why are we bad at
collective
collective uh sense-making and
collective agency
one reason is that we have delegated too
much to to the market because we
we have so we are so bad at collectively
making sense
of things so then it's better to say
well let's just rely on on
on the market instead of trying to
figure um
things out so so that is one reason but
then the other reason is that
in this post-modern philosophical
society that we
live in right now uh that there is no
real philosophical
foundation to rank values
to this to decide collectively on for
example to take a crude example
what should we produce in society should
we produce
theater or pornography we can't really
say
because i mean who am i to say what you
should consume and
what's right and wrong and we have this
value relativity
so then it's much more easy to just say
well let the market sort that out
we let the market decide and then we
don't need to be disgusting whether we
can have
value hierarchies or or not and if those
hierarchies could be
universal or if they are always just the
power structures that
some people are trying to impose on on
on others
so um even though i appreciate very much
post modern philosophy and insights and
of course a deep insight of postmodern
philosophy is the existence
of these collective imaginaries and
how they have power over us and how they
also
have our power structures in in
themselves
so that's very important uh postmodern
insights but then if you take the
postmodern philosophy a
few steps too far then you end up in a
value
relativism and that has had the effect
that even though most postmodern
philosophers are
very critical towards the market
this philosophy has still enabled the
market
to take a very dominant position
in our world and i would even argue
that and
as some philosophers say that each
collective imaginary that we have
always needs a fundamental authority
to anchor this relatively random
collective imaginary
in and during a huge
span of human history
usually our collective imaginaries were
were anchored in
god religion god god had the right
answer
the right answer was in the holy book so
that sort of
put an anchor to to this fairly random
collective imaginary then through the
enlightenment
in in the collective imaginary of of
reason and science
their science became the anchoring
element so
we could find the truth through science
and if we hadn't found the truth yet
science and a combination of science and
reason
would help us find the truth of course
this is something that the postmodern
worldview is
deconstructing correctly so saying
that that every
uh collective imaginary and every
fundamental authority
is just a human construct so god
and science are just human constructs
and therefore not
absolute anchoring points and claiming
correctly
that in today's world there is no
absolute anchor point
that is correct but then we still need
an anchoring point that is why we
invented god
in the first place so then today i claim
the market is
fulfilling that function
even though that was not the intention
of the post-modern
philosophers that is still the actual
effect
so we have a relative very relativistic
post-modern world
view but still our social imaginary
today our social world
is very much anchored in in the market
and i think that what needs to happen
now in this shift that we are going
through
we we need to change that and we need to
in order to do that we we need to
become aware of the importance of our
collective imaginary
and not just be subject to a randomly
constructed
collective imaginary or a collective
imaginary that
has been constructed intentionally
by some sort of um special interest
it has to be a collective imaginary that
that serves humanity as a whole and also
the planet
and all of that and that needs to be
anchored in some sort of
new meta-narrative but the postmodern
philosophers are right in claiming that
every meta-narrative is man-made
that is true so therefore
we need to co-create and co-construct
the new meta
narrative and holding that
knowing that it's not given by god or
given by nature
but as a co-constructed narrative
or narratives because i'm come back to
that or
also later i don't think that we are
moving into or we shouldn't be moving
into just
one mono
culture for the whole globe the future
will
contain many different narratives
but in order for those narratives and
those cultures
to actually be able to live together and
and enrich each other's by giving us
many perspectives of the world
we still need some sort of holding
containers
the story about this good multicultural
society that we can agree upon otherwise
we would never be able to exercise
our collective imaginary freedom
and we would never be able to to solve
some of the
these crises we have in today's meta
crisis
like the environmental problems yeah i
hear you
yeah beautiful thank you for that okay
let me see let me see if i can
say some um things that may in fact be
helpful maybe we can build a little bit
from them together
cool okay help us all understand this
now and why
oh no that's not my job here i'm taking
us
it's i'm taking us into a nosedive all
right okay okay here it is
so part of the issue we face is that
at least psychologically speaking if we
undergo a kind of transformative process
well that's that's
that can be chaotic almost by definition
very uncertain and we're not sure what's
going to emerge on the other side it's
one of the reasons why we might not like
to do it
so this idea this uh this this
post-modern critique
this recognition that much of our
knowledge building um is in fact built
on
a kind of a set of perspectives that can
be critiqued
and cannot in fact serve as these
absolute
grounding points around which everything
can orient
but it's like okay it's like you
challenge that pick away at that
it's like okay there we go now we're
getting into some of the stuff that's
part of the meaning crisis this famous
position of the death of god that nature
that nature speaks to
a kind of breakdown in coherence we
might say
an anchoring pillar of coherence but
what we want to recognize
is that um okay uh we're deeply involved
in the creation of the fabric
which in fact um is the coherence making
structure
between us and then the question is how
can we
not just coherence making but but also
structuring and making our society
function
efficiently and i think we should we
should also say that
this why do we need this anchoring point
well
well it is a huge gift to humanity by
evolution
our ability to construct
the symbolic world and the symbolic
language and this was given to us by
by evolution already back in in stone
age when we started to
to use language to tell stories and we
gathered around the fire and we were
talking stories and trying to make sense
and the fact that we could construct
these different symbolic worlds
had huge survival
value for humans because that made it
possible to us to occupy
many different niches in in
nature and be able to to live anywhere
from
alaska up to um
to greenland so this has had
a huge survival value that we have this
freedom to construct our symbolic world
our
our collective imaginary but the problem
is exactly the one you put in
your finger on for for this to work in
in a human society
we need to live in the same or basically
the same
collective imaginary because otherwise
we can't
communicate and we can't make sense and
we can't cohere
so that so that is that is why we then
invented religion and other tools
to really make it possible for us
to do collective sense making and to
cohere around these
things but when we forget about these
things when we throw out really
religion and when we correctly create um
when we correctly point out that the
scientific perspective of looking at the
world is just one perspective among many
a very important perspective and not a
random perspective
but it it is one perspective among many
then we are starting to lose coherence
and
and we we we have not yet
rediscovered the importance of
uh the collective imaginary because we
can't really see the evolutionary value
of religions
and on those narratives and of course we
are very careful not wanting to replace
a religious narrative with an
ideological
narrative like communism or fascism or
or something we want to we want to keep
the freedom
and the multiple perspectives of our
liberal democratic multicultural world
but we still need to cohere in some
questions
and that is the dilemma that we are in
right now
yeah i feel this this tension point is
something that
uh well of course it's
critical and deeply
it's something that's a big part of your
work it's something that is
certainly a point of real
real interest and i'm committed to this
tension in an important sense with this
project and with
with all the relationships i'm forming i
find
because it turns out this seems to me
that the dynamics of relationship itself
right
how we show up yeah within self
but then also with each other there's we
have this capacity
to tune in together we have this
capacity to
share in perception to share in
expression
to transform our shared capacity for
seeing the world and it's
something like transformation through a
dialogical process together
whether in ceremony whether just in
friendship right
um that we i think it's from that kind
of source
that we can begin to feel fundamentally
what a mode or a way of being in
coherence with each other
is even if we don't in fact know the
fixed and final answer of things which
isn't what we're looking for
no but we can find a way in
it's like just to go better on this
conversation
those of those of um you are still
listening the first 25 minutes
for me this conversation has been a lot
has been listening
right and it's been a beautiful
listening and
what you've presenced has enabled us
with so many concepts and a whole
context to play with right and
and see through um and now
it comes to this point where okay how do
i find
myself in this and it's not about
finding myself as an isolated entity but
it's
how can i add to this so that we
all of a sudden can begin to share in
something together
knowing that we're not going to solve
everything but we can't i don't know
and as you pointed out this process is
emergent so we can't plan this
and and we can't figure out the the the
end result but we can still facilitate
and
and be active participants in this
process but then we come back to what
where you were going before and i
deviated a little bit when you wanted to
introduce the the psychological
perspective
in this because when we move into these
shifts the deeper these shifts
are the more turbulent our whole
world is becoming
and and to not completely freak out as
an individual in this
shift and perhaps even as an individual
be able to actively contribute and
become a
co-creator in this shift that
demands a lot of psychological
capabilities uh on our
from from our side and i know that that
that
you have spoken on your podcasts uh
about uh adult developmental
theory and the importance of of doing
inner work and constantly knowing that
we are on this
lifelong journey of in the maturation so
if we use the language of
professor robert keegan
if if you are in a socialized mind if
your consciousness and your your
sense-making system is
in what he calls a socialized mind
then you are very much dependent on
um an outside source
for for both your world view your your
values and for an anchoring point
and and you cannot really see the
culture
that that you are living within and you
can't
take your own values in that culture as
an object for
reflection whereas when you come a
little bit longer on your lifelong
maturation
and you perhaps start perceiving and
making meaning from a perspective
of a self-authoring mind then you can
start to
reflect on your own values you can start
to reflect on
on on your culture and then you can a
little bit
distance yourself from your culture
and and and to look at your culture from
the outside and your values from the
outside
and that is a prerequisite for you to at
all to be able to be an active
participant in this process without
completely freaking out
and it is this freaking out that we see
in many places in the world
today where people are look are so
afraid of going into this
this shift and looking for security
and in many cases they are looking for
security in the form of an
authoritarian leader or from a dogmatic
religion or just something to hold on to
in this
chaos that they are uh so afraid of
of steps stepping into but but the more
grounded you are in yourself and the
more connected you are
with your own internal values and your
own internal
compass the more you could could dare
letting go and stepping into the chaos
and to become an active
co-creator conscious co-creator of what
wants to emerge
that's beautifully said yeah i would i
i really want to get into that but it's
come to me i'd like to share a story
with you
do you mind no i'm interested okay
it flagged up when you um i mentioned
the word turbulence
you know and um i my body
felt all of a sudden the turbulence of
um
being in a plane when it's turbulent and
you know this is uh this is not a
pleasant thing i've done quite a bit of
flying i i'm sure you've done a lot of
flying right
and you know you can get used to it a
little bit but
i've always been a bit of a nervous
flyer let's say
and there was this one time i um i was
traveling in america
after i finished a degree there and i
had just spent um
a night or a few nights in vegas and i
had stayed out most of the night and i
had to catch a plane i think at like 3
a.m to chicago
and so you know i was
quite you know uh switched on let's say
i got on this plane and we took off and
it was the the worst turbulence i've
ever experienced like
so bad that um it got to a point where
people were screaming throughout the
plane you know and um
there was this sense of okay all right
this may be
maybe this is it you know i've never
heard a plane so
so loud and then it got quite quiet
and i've i've rarely told this story
and it's funny because i can't remember
the face of the
of the man who was sitting next to me
but i remember we were holding hands
and um all of a sudden um
people started to talk to each other it
went from
shrieks to all of a sudden a whole plane
in conversation
and i was holding hands with this with
this man i was trying to comfort him in
some sense
and it stayed terrible um the turbulence
right up until we landed but we landed
and there's just something about
and it you know it's ephemeral thing i
i'm not in touch with anyone and
it's a while ago now but there's
something about
a group of people finding each other
to converse with you know a kind of
comforting of each other and i wasn't
giving up right and
um you know this metaphor isn't gonna
take us exactly where we need to go
because there's a sense in which we were
just looking for security and we weren't
really creating our way out of it
but there's something beautiful we can
do when it
comes to facing turbulence when it comes
to
facing chaos and that's we can in fact
hold hands and be together
and it's there's really no other way to
do it
it's it's it's um no other certain
capacity to breathe
yeah exactly if
or project that fear in various
uh directions and that that is also of
course a human instinct that
yeah if we feel this fear try to find a
scapegoat
to try to find them that we could uh
scapegoat and project our fears towards
yeah
but it's exciting now you know there is
genuine hope because
what what i feel a lot is i and i've
been
seeking to engage in transformative
conversations for
a long time and i'm feeling that there
is
um a really a burgeoning
interest and there's a lot of available
energy wonderful projects you know
including the stowa rebel wisdom
starting communities but
many discord communities there's a voice
craft collective
which is a group of us who get together
to have conversations and experimenting
with ways we can
effectively be generative together
um and it this ties into i think
some of the inner developmental um
stuff a direction we might take but it
seems like um
worthwhile to just nod to the fact that
i really
in the face of so much turbulence
um and we can it's a bit like a roller
coaster you know
i mean i certainly feel hope sometimes
begin to fade but i also
feel a resounding a resounding
note of it um and so there's
along with all of these podcasts you
know there's genuine invitations to
people and i think that's something
important that we both
that we both appreciate is the
importance of extending invitations to
actively participate in this moment in a
way that's
valuable for you as an individual but
fundamentally nested and interconnected
with what is
valuable and worthwhile to be a part of
for the whole as well
absolutely we we we we need we need um
[Music]
many of us to to step up and and then
i'm
not talking about hundreds of people i'm
not talking about thousands of people
i'm talking about millions
of people that that needs to step up at
this
point and to help to co-create
through this turbulence co-create
through these turbulence that
that you metaphorically was was speaking
about before
and and that might be a good point to to
go back to
uh the book you mentioned lena's and
my book the nordic secret because
that that book really tells the story
about
how we in the nordic countries when we
were
in this last latest
very important societal shift in our
countries when
we went from being the poorest
non-democratic
religious agrarian societies
at the end of the 1800s to
just a few generations later being the
richest the happiest most stable
industrial democracies in in the world
and that was a period of turbulence and
in many places in in
in in in the world certainly in in
continental europe
this transition from more or less
agrarian uh authoritarians societies
into uh democracies that that was very
turbulent and it was a lot of
violence violence and there was a lot of
war
whereas in in scandinavia we managed
this very
peacefully and um
i've been in into very interested in
this connection between our
personal inner development and societal
change
ever since i left banking more than 10
years ago and
set up my own foundation in sweden
called the
oak island foundation yeah credit
but it wasn't until uh five years ago
that i discovered
together with leona that i was really
trying to reinvent the wheel that this
understanding of the connection between
our personal inner development
and societal change that that was
actually a perspective
that most if not all
intellectuals and politicians
in scandinavia 150 years ago
had on the world and this understanding
of the importance of
personal development um actually turned
into national policy
in in both denmark and in norway and
in sweden because we had intellectuals
and politicians who saw this turbulence
coming
that they they knew that
industrialization and urbanization
and democracy was coming and
they were really truly committed to
build democracy but also
they knew not the least from the german
philosophers gert and schiller and
herder
von humboldt also danish philosophy
kierkegaard
that in terms of rapid social change and
turbulence
we want to have a hand to hold on to as
you said
we want to we as humans it's so easy for
us humans
to want to hold on to an external
authority
to a dogmatic religion or to an
authoritarian leader
but these politicians and intellectuals
they didn't want to be authoritarian
leaders they were
firmly committed to to build strong
democracies
and they knew that the only way to build
strong democracies are
to build them from from bottom up
and in order to do that they wanted to
create the possibility for for many
citizens
to be able to do the work of inner
development
and be able to connect to their inner
compass
to become self-authoring or starting the
process of
self-authoring that we that we just
mentioned
and do you know how they did that
well i've heard you discuss it a few
times but i'm interested i'm interested
for you to sort of
take us through it again because yeah so
this is something that
please yeah so so i joking you can
jokingly um sometimes called
what they did was that they created a
lot of retreat centers
and that is actually what they did i
mean they were not called retreat
centers back then but they were
centers often out in nature uh
committed to programs of of of
learning but also inner development and
discovering
and trying to connect with your your
true
authentic values and becoming
self-authoring
and by the turn of the last century year
1900 there were actually a hundred cents
like this just in denmark
75 in norway and 150 in sweden
where young adults usually in their in
their 20s
could later on with full state subsidies
spend
up to six months in retreat in order to
connect with themselves and each other
and
talk about society talk about technology
talk about this shift
that they were in and in that way become
conscious co-creators of the
the new society and when this program
was at it
its height actually 10 of each young
generation participated
in programs like this and of course that
created a a critical mass or a tipping
point in the complex system we would say
today using using that language
and what was especially beautiful in
this case i think was that the
participants
in these programs they came from all
different
layers of society and actually majority
of the participants were from farming or
working class background so you had
these conscious co-creators not just in
a small elite somewhere in society but
but
fairly well distributed all over and
and that managed to create this tipping
point
now now of course we are starting to
lose this in scandinavia
and we discussed that in our book as as
well because
after the second world war we we started
to
change world view again and we forgot
about
the importance of our inner world and
the possibility of the lifelong
development that we had
learned from the german bildung
philosophers i just
mentioned and we instead turned to the
anglo-saxon world we turned to oxford
and cambridge and to the us
and and there it was still the old world
view on
loch ger with them our mind as a
rational machine and
not at all the focus on lifelong in the
development and
the importance of that both for
individuals
but also for society so that's the story
and
and i don't think that this is a
blueprint for how we should do it today
but
certainly it's a case study showing that
what we are talking about
on on pods like this about the
importance of inner development
in these shifts that that is not just
some
new interesting idea it has actually
been tried
large scale full scale in three
countries
a little bit different implementation in
each country and it actually worked in
all of those
countries today we might make use of
technology to bring down the costs
for this and one initiative that i'm
involved with is the 29k
initiative which is a digital platform
for personal growth a non-profit open
source
co-created platform that i take the
the liberty to to point our listeners to
29k.org yeah beautiful well i'm
i'm really looking forward to seeing how
that develops i've checked it out and
i'll include some links
um but let me let me see if i can
tie a couple things together here
i want to see if i can bring in
this this
need we have to do something about the
absence of a meta narrative we can all
participate
in but perhaps to play with
maybe play with some different language
there um because
it's unclear to me
whether we can frame things in terms of
meta-narrative um
i think unless we want to say something
like
the meta narrative is that which
continually um
it fuels itself through
a reciprocal process of extending
invitations
for people to participate and develop
the narrative or
create their own narratives in some
fundamental sense but i think the link
in fact like the imminent
um link or maybe like the where i at
least
feel i can where my hope let's say
grounds
where my hope is grounded is again back
to
relationship and it's something
like that
almost there
hmm it's it's part of this issue we have
is trust
you know is his trust in the kind of
relationality that is the very essence
of the commons
right we've spoken about the market and
we can talk about the state and
in fact in a conversation i heard john
viveki have with jordan hall and greg
henriquez which i really recommend um
people check out um i can include a link
to that as well
jordan sort of offered a formal
articulation of the relationship between
the commons the market and the state and
was sort of
speaking about how to reinvigorate
the commons which has in fact broken
down we might look at it as a kind of
sense of
um fellowship or kinship fundamentally a
kind of
communal friendship right mediated by
an effective and vital let's say
collective imaginary to use some of the
language we've been speaking about so
far
that's a kind of and of course the
collective imaginary
it's is itself such a comma
yes itself such such a
a common and if we do it and if we don't
take care of
of it as a common then then we will uh
perhaps have the tragedy of the common
yes
yeah beautiful okay so so they are
effectively they're playing the same
role here
we can sort of substitute one one for
the other
so to um so so how then
fundamentally like this is this is one
of the problems we have to
we have to um address on an ongoing
basis
how can we open interactions
how can we extend invitations how can we
participate with each other
when the turbulence of the difference
in shared sense of collective imaginary
is present and my proposition would be
something like
we mentioned in a development we
mentioned self-authoring and what have
you
but this metaphor of the holding hands
you know
there's there's something in there there
there is a
felt sense it's almost like on the
breath it's it's just a fluency of
breathing in and out being able to just
slow down and it's it's like
metaphorically for me it's like
connecting with the person's eyes you
know it's just seeing that little bit
deeper
and all of a sudden the complexity of
our potential
right that's in some sense um
transcendent to whatever the collective
imaginary is of the time
it's like a source to to draw from
and it's it's this it's such a beautiful
thing that just with
almost with the right intention with the
with the right feeling
with the right extending of the hand you
know that
just it's a little moment and then all
of a sudden we can begin to
just get to know each other a little bit
some words that comes to my mind here
are the words of
my my friend the african philosopher
bio akumolafe he sometimes says
um my ancestors tell me
we are in an emergency we have to slow
down
and that is so counterintuitive to our
western
mind but i think that is what what you
are talking about here that
in this turbulence we we might just want
to rush in
and do things and try to make meaning
and solve things but
the way we might need to do at least
first
is to slow down and and to reach deep
into
uh ourselves and and to see
what ways we can contribute and how we
in the best way can be meaningful
participants
in this process because i think you're
putting the finger on the right thing
here
that we have to look at this as a
process
it's not one meta-narrative we want to
reach it's not
one of society we want to need
technological change is now so so fast
that
society and everything is developing so
quickly
that we cannot say what the world will
be like in
20 years perhaps not even 10 years but
when we cannot be
certain about the good outcome of the
process
then we can't not just give up and say
okay
then let's just see what happens no then
our
focus needs to shift from the outcome to
the process
and instead of asking ourselves what is
the good outcome
to ask ourselves just like you did what
is the good
process how can we talk about a good
process
and how can we all become and
enable ourselves and empower ourselves
to become
active and conscious agents in that
process that never-ending process
yes yeah yeah beautifully said
so i just encourage everyone you know um
to
check out the links here in this
conversation to
all the projects thomas is involved with
and here too these are genuine
invitations to
involve yourself in just this kind of
process
there's a vision a collaborative vision
developing um i that i at least see
in this metacultural space that looks
something like a networked group of
communities there's movement between and
there's
there's elders and wisdom keepers and
people who connect at a level of feeling
and people who connect a level of
thinking and
and in a recognition of the importance
of the integration between these
functions
um i talk sometimes about
integrating the thinking and the doing
and and and the being or the becoming
part so uh yeah so we can't just be in
our heads but we need
theory and we need we need understanding
um and then we need
entrepreneurship we need people who are
actually doing things
in this field experimenting in this
field
building bridges into this fog foggy
future that we don't know where it is
but we
still need to do things experiment
and then what i tend to forget the most
being mostly in the thinking and doing
side but we we need the being and we
need the becoming
and and we need to slow down and
to to reach deep into our being and
becoming to see how we can best
contribute in this process
yeah well it's beautiful thomas um yeah
you know
i think we're nearing the end of our
time here but i am curious to ask you
just a final question
uh and you can answer shortly if you
like but
uh that is i'm interested in what's next
for you
you know is it um in terms of if you
would
write another book but not so much about
the book but in
what what's what's on the cusp for you
what are the ideas the activities
what do you feel is drawing you into the
future at the moment
i just came back from a very interesting
experiment at um
my foundations island outside stockholm
the
the oak island ear credit where we had
uh
gathered a few um
uh people who from the crowd that we
gathered at the emerge gathering in kiev
last year and we were experimenting
there a little bit
with collective sense making
so we gather a small group of
european facilitators people with
decades of experience of facilitating
group
processes and and to see whether whether
we could
tap deeper into this being or deeper
into this becoming
in order to be able to
harvest the collective uh
intelligence in this group
and to see how such of a facilitation
is is is possible
and we did some interesting uh
experimentation in this direction at the
emerge gathering in kiev last year
and we came even even further here uh
during this in this small group at the
exhaust
so i'm very interested to see
can we as humanity learn
or relearn to
connect together in a deeper
personal connection in a group of people
and then try to understand
and communicate and together make sense
from that greater whole that emerges
between us and this is still
just very very uh uh
early stages but i think it's something
in that direction we
we we need to go we we need in this
transition
to find
not just new perspectives not just
develop ourselves
and mature as individuals but we also
need to find
new ways of making sense and
there of course john verwege is talking
about
various psycho technologies and
those psycho technologies needs to be
collective
in a collective sense making so
experimenting in this field right now
gives me gives me a lot of energy
yeah yeah me too me too well
um look i mean
believe me i could take this
conversation in about five hours worth
of different direction but we will have
to leave that i think for
for another occasion it's been really
beautiful to get to know you a little
bit and
have this conversation and man looking
forward to
looking forward to the co-creation the
ongoing co-creation of this future
and also yeah there is turbulence
but um i appreciate the work you're
doing so thank you for joining me
thank you tim and thank you for doing
this podcast and connecting a lot of
people with
interesting ideas in these turbulent
times
thank you